Welcome. This is my first time I'm talking at FOSDEM.
You can follow along the slides via the link.
You can follow along with the slides via the link.
By the time this airs, I hope to be able to provide subtitles for download.
The content will be close to speaker notes you can see on the right hand or on the bottom,
depending on the screen size of your machine.
My name is André Jaenisch.
I'm working as a Software engineer at Jambit,
which is a medium-sized software provider in Germany.
This talk has nothing to do with my company.
Instead, it's something I'm really interested in myself.
Since this reveal.js presentation is pre-recorded using OBS Studio,
I'm kindly asking you to ask your questions at the end.
Also it would be really great
if I would be allowed to add your comments to the presentation slides afterwards.
Please let me know, if you're willing to opt-in into that.
Unless otherwise noted, the content is made available under
the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license.
Today I want to tell you something about Eleventy.
Eleventy is a simpler Static Site Generator.
You will learn something about the people behind it,
why it was build,
where you can read more about it,
what the community did with it,
where you can ask questions or how you can help.
Along the way we will see some possums.
Eleventy's mascot is one. His name is Edison.
The idea spun from James Williamson, who sadly passed away.
What does Eleventy mean?
As preparation for this talk, I did some research.
Although I couldn't find the trivia behind its name,
there are some interesting tidbits associated with it.
The term „Eleventy” came up in Old English, around mid 19th century.
It became more popular with The Lord of the Rings by J. R. R. Tolkien.
This image here is taken from a video game.
Meet Zach.
He's the person, who created Eleventy.
Next to static site generators he's also interested into Web Fonts.
You might also know him from conferences.
Now, the important questions.
Why a possum?
I did some research, actually.
Here, we see a baby opposum.
But there are other mammals called possums which live in Australia.
I guess, it's American slang term to call them the same.
Now the more important question:
Why does Eleventy use an opposum as a mascot?
The answer is: 42.
The real answer is a homage to Zach's friend.
So now:
Before we can continue, it is worth to define what we mean by Static Site Generator.
I brought you a definition by Phil Hawksworth who works also at Netlify like Zach.
Think of a Static Site Generator
as a script which takes in data, content and templates
processes them, and outputs a folder full of all the resultant pages and assets.
We will meet data, content and templates later again.
What makes Eleventy special?
There are a lot of Static Site Generators out there.
They come in different shapes and forms.
Personally, I used Jekyll, Hugo, Hexo and Grav before.
But Eleventy has something, that makes it stand out to me.
From its initial design goals, these are:
Flexibility
Betting on JavaScript
and not being a JavaScript framework.
If you want to find more on Zach's thoughts on this
check out his introduction blog post.
I want to look into them in detail now.
Flexibility
With Eleventy you can mix and match template engines at will.
Say, you have a Liquid template because you started off with Jekyll.
At one point, you want to benefit from some Nunjucks feature.
It's easy with Eleventy!
Eleventy even allows you to define a template inheritance chain
- between different template languages if you want!
That means, you can start with a Liquid template, load that
with a Nunjucks template which gets loaded by an
You are also free to choose input and output directory.
Mustache template, for example.
mustache template, for example.
You are also free to choose input and output directory.
Or you even use Eleventy to transform a single file!
The JavaScript ecosystem is vast as you probably know!
I ran modulecounts against different module repositories.
NPM clocks at about 1.5 million repositories
in January 2021.
That's a 1.5 and five zeroes!
The next largest repository is Maven for Java which contains about 370k modules.
So Node.js has four times the amount of choices than Java!
That means, you will likely find a library for every problem you can think of.
Let's benefit from this fact.
I hear your argument:
That would be true for other Static Site Generators.
Say Gatsby.
Which leds us to …
Not being a JavaScript framework
Unlike Gatsby, Eleventy does not force you to learn a JavaScript framework.
It's plain Node.js.
It does not recommend or enforce
certain frameworks (by default).
That being said, I'm aware of experiments to use it with Svelte or Vue.js.
It neither forces you to use a certain template language.
More about that later.
Where is it used?
Okay, that's all good and fine. But is it actually used?
I brought you some examples.
Take the Chrome Dev Summit.
Which was built with Eleventy.
Or the CSS Tricks conference page.
Or if you want to take something different - what about the ESLint website.
If you want to browse them yourself, head over to the Leaderboard which has over 450 entries.
Okay, perhaps you are more interested in individuals.
Fine.
Chris Coyier from CSS-Tricks says:
„Eleventy is almost fascinatingly simple.”
Or take Sara Soueidan, a freelance designer:
„Eleventy is a killer static site generator. That's all.”
We will hear more from Andy Bell later
who said „Jekyll is dead to me”
With that strong enthusiasm, there are a lot of people who support Eleventy financially.
You can even see some organisations here, Sanity or Picalilli.
According to Open Collective there are more like for example ESLint which we saw before or Frontend Weekly,
but they did not make it to Gold sponsorship and thus don't appear on the screenshot.
What can you build with Eleventy?
Recall the definition of a Static Site Generator?
They provide pages and assets.
So you can basically build everything that consists of pages.
Blogs is the default idea.
Or perhaps a website.
But if you level up to JAMstack, you can take it further.
Remember: JAMstack stands for JavaScript, APIs and Markup.
For example, I showed you conference pages before,
but you can build whole conferences.
Now, what blew my mind was this Lightning Talk by Doctor Dan Fascia,
who granted me permission to use YouTube screenshots and share them with you.
He works as Radiologist and Health Technologist.
So not exactly what most of us do here for a living.
The first two are websites,
are websites where he could repurpose some Nunjucks components, which were already built.
But the last one is a whole conference built with Eleventy and some APIs.
Go, watch the video.
After my talk, please.
So, let's shortly recap, what makes Eleventy so special.
It's easy to get started.
You have the full power of the NPM ecosystem.
You have plugins which fall into three categories.
Filters
which take some input or take some content and transform it into something else which is then used in-place.
You have shortcodes
which can be thought of as a macro.
That means they are placeholder for a larger code snippet.
And you have transforms
which operate on a whole file.
Then you can write your code or your content in Markdown.
Or HTML.
Remember that was another pillar of Static Site Generator!
You have support for different template languages.
By default Angular comes with
HTML, Markdown, JavaScript, Liquid, Nunjucks
HTML, Markdown, JavaScript, Liquid, Nunjucks,
Handlebars, Mustache, Embedded JavaScript and Haml and Pug
Pug was formerly known as Jade.
You have collections.
Collections are generated by default from tags which you define in your frontmatter.
But you also have different other ways to define them,
for example you can take a collection
filter it and create a new collection from that.
Or you can use a file glob.
Then, you have async data
which can be used in data directory files.
Personally I use it for example for a static file
where I maintain events I'm interested in
But you can also API for it.
For example I'm pulling my tweets onto my website using data directory files.
Last but not least: Pagination.
Pagination can be used to create pages from data.
Pagination can be used to create pages from data
by defining a page size of 1.
This way you can have an API or a headless CMS
and generate static sites from it.
Before we go into technical details,
I want to show you how the community might help you along the journey.
There are different places where the community comes together.
Originally, there was discussions or interaction via Twitter.
Then, GitHub introduced Discussions
and we use them next to plain old issues.
If you have more shortlived questions,
hop onto the latest addition: a Discord server.
Once you are looking into Eleventy issues, you will find something different.
Most issues get closed quite quickly.
And you will find a comment by Zach that says
This issue is umm… This repository is managed via Lodash issue management
So if you are an Open Source maintainer this might be interesting for you as well.
Basically you close most of the issues
except bugs and then you use a GitHub issue filter for the labeled issues you closed
and let people upvote to determine in which order you should implement the enhancement.
Of course people are blogging.
With a quick search you will find plenty of getting started tutorials.
So I brought you some more advanced topics
which might help you learn some new tricks
or blend into JAMstack.
You will find blog articles about data, content and template here.
Again, this makes up a Static Site Generator.
Speaking of…
the community developed lots of plugins.
I only brought you a small subset here.
There is no hard rule, but by convention, most plugins start with eleventy-plugin.
There are plenty of more.
But if you feel you don't want to develop everything by hand,
the community also provided starter repositories.
As you can see the most repositories have a really good Lighthouse score.
So you have a great start and take it from there.
Again, this is only a small subset of what's available.
Say, I convinced you to get started with Eleventy.
If you want to use a guideline to follow along,
use 11ty Rocks!
Another project in that spirit can be found at 11ty Recipes.
If you need inspiration,
take a look at Eleventy Themes.
Be aware, that Eleventy does not have a theming system itself.
Last but not least,
the hashtag BuiltWithEleventy can be used to collect pages built with it.
And this site here associates the group behind it.
If you take a look you will even large enterprises betting on Eleventy!
I'm not the first one who tries to introduce a wider audience to Eleventy.
In fact, I can recommend these two links.
The first one is a podcast and the second a YouTube list.
David will give you a nice overview like I did here.
The playlist shows some real-world examples or can teach you even more tricks.
Okay, Eleventy got some traction.
That led to first training courses coming up.
Perhaps, you feel better with spending some money
to get high-quality stuff in return.
Fear not, Andy Bell has you covered.
I haven't taken his course personally, but I only hear positive feedback so far.
If you want to have something sweat and short,
Stephanie Eckles have you covered.
Not convinced?
What about learning with Jason then?
He recorded a video where Zach himself shows you the ropes.
I urge you: if this presentation convinced you, please donate.
This will help sustain the development.
There are even some perks you can gain for it.
For example, if you logged in into Eleventy website, you will get a more powerful search.
Or your avatar will displayed on almost all pages you can find in the Eleventy documentation.
So this is your chance! Use it!
If you don't have the money, no problem.
Please star the repo or/and tell a friend about how awesome it is!
As you can see I used plenty of pictures and here are the sources I used
and the licenses as far as I know them.
And with this I want to thank you for listening and
now we have time for questions.